Guide to the Patrick Joseph Sullivan Diaries 1905-1944 MS 3225
New-York Historical Society
Patrick Joseph Sullivan Diaries
1905-1944
New-York Historical Society
Sullivan, Patrick Joseph, 1874-1944
MS 3225
2 Linear feet in 2 record cartons
This collection consists of diaries documenting the work and family life of Patrick Joseph Sullivan (1874-1944), a fuel inspector for the New York City Department of Education. The diaries date from 1905 to 1944.
Arrangement
The diaries are arranged chronologically.
Biographical / Historical
Patrick Joseph Sullivan was born in New York City on March 18, 1874 to Patrick J. Sullivan and Ellen O'Brien Sullivan, both of whom had emigrated from Ireland in the mid-19th century.
By 1905, Sullivan was working for the NYC Department of Education as fuel inspector, a job he would hold for the rest of his life. On November 9, 1910, he married Mary (Mamie) Coughlin at St. Monica's Roman Catholic Church in Manhattan. The couple soon settled in Corona, Queens, where they raised 9 children: Frank, Madeleine, Honoria (Nonie), Rosemary, James, Alice, Daniel, Geraldine, and Joan.
Patrick Joseph Sullivan died suddenly on February 23, 1944.
Access Restrictions
Materials in this collection may be stored offsite. For more information on making arrangements to consult them, please visit www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Maureen E. Lyons Levine, 2014
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of small bound volumes used as diaries by Patrick Joseph Sullivan (1874-1944). Sullivan, the son of Irish immigrants, worked as a fuel inspector for the New York City Department of Education in the early 20th century, and lived in Corona, Queens with his wife and their 9 children. Diary entries begin on February 24, 1905, and end on February 23, 1944, the date of his death. In brief daily entries, Sullivan records the bare facts of his activities at work and at home. At the beginning and end of many of the diaries are records of household accounts, as well as phone numbers of co-workers, relatives and friends.
Sullivan's notes about his work include details such as which schools he visited in various boroughs, and the amount and cost of coal or wood delivered:
September 2, 1908: "Rep[orted] at B[oard] of Ed. Worked inside until 2 p.m. Sent to Boyce and Barnes Co. yard in Astoria to make arrangements with wood contractor."
October 18, 1911: "Wednesday, Bklyn P.S. 146. Yard coal. Stove coal Tick 26529."
In the entries about his life with his family in Queens, Sullivan records special occasions, visits with relatives and friends, trips to the movies, and his children's weekend outings in the same matter-of-fact manner:
November 9, 1910: "Married in St. Monica's Church, Father Jordan officiating."
July 4 1913: "Holiday- Baby girl born at 8 a.m. on this glorious day."
May 6, 1928: "Nonie and Rosemary to the 9 o'clock Mass- Jim in bed sick- Madeleine and Francis to the 11:15 Mass- Mamie and myself to the 10 o'clock Mass...I was down to Insp. Dolan's house to the wake. Mrs Dolan died on Friday. All the inspectors except Ryan and Hanity at the wake- home by 1:30 p.m."
Diaries.; New York (N.Y.) Department of Education; Civil service positions--New York (State)--New York.; School administrators -- New York (State) -- New York.; School management and organization -- New York (State) -- New York.; New York (N.Y.) -- Social life and customs -- 20th century.; Queens (New York, N.Y.)
- Diaries, 1905-1906 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
- Diaries, 1906-1908 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
- Diaries, 1908-1909 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
- Diaries, 1909 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
- Diaries, 1909-1910 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
- Diaries, 1910-1911 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
- Diaries, 1911-1912 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 7)
- Diaries, 1912-1914 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 8)
- Diaries, 1914-1915 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 9)
- Diaries, 1916-1918 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 10)
- Diaries, 1918-1920 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 11)
- Diaries, 1920-1922 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 12)
- Diaries, 1922-1924 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 13)
- Diaries, 1924-1926 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 14)
- Diaries, 1926-1928 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 15)
- Diaries, 1928-1929 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 1)
- Diaries, 1929-1931 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 2)
- Diaries, 1931 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 3)
- Diaries, 1931-1933 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 4)
- Diaries, 1933-1934 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 5)
- Diaries, 1934-1936 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 6)
- Diaries, 1936-1937 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 7)
- Diaries, 1937-1939 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 8)
- Diaries, 1939-1941 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 9)
- Diaries, 1941-1942 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 10)
- Diaries, 1942-1943 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 11)
- Diaries, 1942-1944 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 12)